Carel Bailey Germain Papers, 1922-1998
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Carel B. Germain papers
1922-1998
1970-1995
Germain, Carel B.
301
40 boxes (14.4 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Professor of social work. Germain taught graduate courses that focused on the ecological approach to social work theory and practice. Her subject files are voluminous and contain material on a wide range of topics relevant to the teaching and practice of social work. Material includes biographical information, writings, correspondence, and audio tapes of Germain teaching Ego Psychology. Correspondents include Ann Hartman, Joan Laird, Alex Gitterman, and Anita Lightburn.
Carel Bailey was born in San Francisco on 23 October 1916 to Thomas J. and Lera Bailey. She graduated from the University of California, Berkeley in 1937 with a degree in economics, and lived and worked in the Bay Area until moving east in 1958. She married William Germain in 1941, and after raising twin daughters earned her MSW (1961) and DSW (1971) at the Columbia University School of Social Work. Upon completion of her MSW degree, Germain embarked on a distinguished career as a professor and prolific author in the field of social work. She taught at the University of Maryland for several years and, after finishing her doctorate, was appointed with tenure, first to Columbia University and then to the University of Connecticut, where she taught until her retirement in 1987. Germain offered graduate level courses that focused on the ecological approach to social work theory and practice. Although she was also versed in the history of social work, she only once offered a course on the subject (in the Spring 1973 semester at Columbia). Germain wrote seven books, the most important of which were The Life Model of Social Work Practice, 1980 (co-authored with Alex Gitterman) and Human Behavior in the Social Environment: An Ecological View, 1991. She also published widely in professional journals and was in great demand as a speaker, guest lecturer, reviewer and author of chapters and introductions for social work anthologies and for books by colleagues. She died in Avon, Connecticut on 3 August 1995.
Germain is perhaps best known for her pioneering work in the "ecological" or "life model" approach to social work practice. She first developed the concept of an "ecological perspective" while teaching at Columbia in the mid-seventies, and later elaborated upon it in collaboration with a colleague, Alex Gitterman. Social work theory and practice had traditionally been based on a Freudian psychotherapeutic model in which diagnosis and treatment focused primarily on the psychology of the individual client and the dynamics of the immediate family. Although clinical social workers had long been aware that people exist in a more extensive social and psychological matrix, the profession lacked a conceptual framework that linked broader environmental and cultural influences to difficulties faced by individual clients. Using metaphors borrowed from the biological definition of ecology ("the relation between living organisms and their environment"), Germain laid the foundation for the needed structure. As she and Gitterman wrote in the 19th Encyclopedia of Social Work, "The ecological perspective makes clear the need to view people and environments as a unitary system within a particular cultural and historical context. Both person and environment can be fully understood only in terms of their relationship, in which each continually influences the other within a particular context. Hence, all concepts derived from the ecological metaphor refer not to environment alone or person alone; rather, each concept expresses a particular person: environment relationship, whether it is positive, negative or neutral." (Germain and Gitterman, 1995) Over time, Germain and Gitterman found that, in addition to its applicability to work with individuals and families, the ecological perspective was also relevant to larger groups, organizations, communities, and to political advocacy in general. They elaborated on this expanded concept in The Life Model of Social Work Practice: Advances in Theory and Practice, 1996.
The Carel Bailey Germain Papers include biographical information; personal and professional correspondence; materials pertaining to Germain's graduate education and her subsequent professional work; research files for specific course offerings and writings; and typed manuscripts of some of her writings.
Note: Some research and subject materials that were originally filed in a single folder were divided into two or more folders for preservation purposes and for ease of handling. In addition, since Germain used teaching materials, research materials and general subject files for books and journal articles coterminously, there is some overlap in the contents of these files; therefore, the purposes of some researchers may require consulting Series III, V, and VI.
This collection is organized into six series:
I. Biographical
II. Education
III. Professional Activities
IV. Correspondence
V. Writings
VI. Subjects
Oversize Materials
Personal and professional correspondence (Series IV) is arranged alphabetically by the correspondent's last name or, where appropriate, by name of institution. All writings (Series V) are in chronological order, and reviews of Germain's books are located at the end of the section relating to each volume. To facilitate cross-referencing, there is an appendix at the end of the finding aid that lists articles and book titles alphabetically as well as chronologically.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
History of the Collection
Carel Bailey Germain donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection from 1984 until her death in 1995. Her family has continued to add to the collection.
Search Terms
Developmental psychology--Research--Sources; Environmental psychology--Research--Sources; Family social work--United States--History--Sources; Human ecology--Research--Sources; Social work education--United States--History--Sources; Social workers--United States--History--Sources; World War, 1939-1945--Personal narratives, American; Germain, Carel B.; Dubos, Rene J., (Rene Jules), 1901-; Gitterman, Alex, 1938- --Correspondence; Hartman, Ann--Correspondence; Reynolds, Bertha Capen, 1885-
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL 1922-95, .8 linear feet.
  This series includes biographical information, obituaries and tributes, memorabilia, memoirs, and photographs. In part, this series documents Germain's girlhood involvement with the Camp Fire Girls in California, a formative experience that instilled a deep love of the natural world and, according to Germain, later contributed to the development of her ecological model of social work theory.
- SERIES II. EDUCATION 1932-94, .4 linear feet.
  This series is arranged chronologically. Although there are some items that relate to Germain's early education or that were incidental to her educational status later in life, the bulk of the series is comprised of notes and other materials generated by doctoral level courses at the Columbia University School of Social Work. Germain cited Lucille Austin, Bernard Barber and Irving Miller as having profoundly influenced her thinking, which might explain why she chose to save materials from their courses.
- SERIES III. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES 1964-95, .3 linear feet.
  This series is arranged by type of activity. It includes papers relating to such activities as committee and board work, thesis and dissertation advising, participation in conferences and seminars, and membership in professional associations. The series also includes some teaching materials.
- SERIES IV. CORRESPONDENCE 1943-95, .8 linear feet.
  Professional correspondence spans Germain's entire career and illustrates both the breadth of her professional interests and the level of respect she earned in the field of social work; it is approximately half incoming and half outgoing. Most of the personal correspondence dates from the mid-1980s, with the exception of a set of letters from William Germain to Carel, written during his tour of duty in World War II. The personal correspondence consists mostly of incoming letters, but some do include Germain's replies.
- SERIES V. WRITINGS 1979-96, 5.3 linear feet.
  This series consists of correspondence, research materials, notes relating to specific writings, and drafts of some writings. It also includes Germain's commentaries on and reviews of writings by peers, articles she wrote for social work publications, as well as forewords, introductions and chapters for books by colleagues. "Research materials--unidentified" (located in Boxes 13 and 14) is a sub-series of "Published works" and pertains to both The Life Model of Social Work Practice: Advances in Theory and Practice, 1996 and to a revised edition of Human Behavior in the Social Environment: An Ecological Approach 1991; the files indicate an overlap, and Germain apparently used them to work on both books simultaneously. Research materials relating to the writing of Germain's books are of interest in that they reveal the steps involved in producing a manuscript and seeing it through to publication. Similarly, extensive correspondence with co-author Alex Gitterman (filed in this series under The Life Model of Social Work Practice, 1980 and The Life Model of Social Work Practice: Advances in Theory and Practice, 1996) offers insight into the collaborative writing process. Series V also contains 1.4 linear feet of data relating to unpublished works, including Germain's dissertation, "Casework and Science: A Study in the Sociology of Knowledge".
- SERIES VI. SUBJECTS, 6.7 linear feet.
  This series contains subject files and is arranged alphabetically. It includes almost half the collection and is comprised of extensive files on a wide range of topics relevant to the teaching and practice of social work, including a substantial section on the history of the profession. There is also .5 linear foot of segments of published proceedings of The National Conference of Social Work and the National Conference on Social Welfare (apparently synonymous), which span but do not include all the years 1926-61. Files in this series are mostly undated, but it seems that Germain collected the material throughout her career. Although Germain read the New York Times and regularly clipped articles that related to her work, space limitations and the ready availability of this source dictated that most of the newsclippings in the subject files could not be retained. (Exceptions include New York Times Magazine articles, subject files comprised primarily of newsclippings, and clippings specifically about social work theory and practice.)
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL
  - Biographical articles, 1971-93, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Curricula vitae, 1988-95, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Condolences, obituaries, gifts in memoriam, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Donation of papers to Sophia Smith Collection, 1984-95, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Campfire Girls, Camp Deep Woods, 1922-60, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Memoirs, 1991-92, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Travel diary, Ireland, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Honors, awards, retirement, 1969-95, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Humorous, anecdotal material, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - General family, 1969, 1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, 1930-94, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Scrapbook, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Scrapbook, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Photo album, Camp Wasibo, 1928-44, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
- SERIES II. EDUCATION
  [See also Series V. "Writings--Unpublished works" for material relating to Germain's dissertation.]
  - Miscellaneous
    - High school graduation, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Transcripts, 1961, 1967, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Doctoral courses
    [See also Series V, Writings--Unpublished works]
    - Course notes, "Social Casework" with Lucille Austin, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 16-18)
    - Course notes, "History and Philosophy of Social Welfare" with Irving Miller, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
    - Course notes, "Sociology of Knowledge" with Bernard Barber, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Course notes, unidentified (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Academic degrees
    - Certificates (Box 3A, Folder 15a)
      [See also Oversize Materials]
- SERIES III. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES
  - Conferences and seminars, 1964-85 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Committee and board work 1984-86 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Dissertation and thesis advising, 1975, 1981, 1989, 1992, 1995, undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Teaching materials
    - Syllabi, bibliographies, references, 1972, 1982, undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Lecture notes, 1973, 1975, 1977, undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Notes, 1972-73, 1987, undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Examples, 1973-90, undated (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - "History of Social Work" (Box 4, Folder 30-31)
  - Writings by peers, 1972, 1987, undated (Box 5, Folder 31a)
  - Writings by students, 1969, 1973, 1977, 1984, undated (Box 5, Folder 31b)
  - Professional associations
    - Council on Social Work Education, 1979-86 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - National Association of Social Workers, 1979-87 (Box 5, Folder 33)
- SERIES IV. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Personal
    - Family
      - General, 1982-93 (Box 6, Folder 34)
      - William Germain, World War II letters (copies, excerpted and typed by Carel Germain), 1943-45 (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - Friends
      - General, A-Z, 1984-95 (Box 6, Folder 36)
      - Bloom, Martin and Lynn, 1989-95 (Box 6, Folder 37)
      - Hartman, Ann, 1993-95 (Box 6, Folder 38)
      - Laird, Joan, 1988-95, undated (Box 6, Folder 39)
      - Lee, Judith, 1980-1995, undated (Box 6, Folder 40)
      - Middleman, Ruth, 1993-95 (Box 6, Folder 41)
      - Ng, Agnes, 1990-94 (Box 6, Folder 42)
      - Patterson, Shirley, 1985-95, undated (Box 6, Folder 43)
      - Zschocke, Thomas, 1993, 1994, undated (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - Unidentified, 1944, 1985, 1993, undated (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Professional
    - Employment, 1969-86, undated (Box 7, Folder 46)
    - Canadian, 1981-90, undated (Box 7, Folder 47)
    - Invitations to participate, A-P, 1973-88 (Box 7, Folder 48)
    - Invitations to participate, R-W, 1973-88 (Box 7, Folder 49)
    - General, A-W, 1961, 1973-94 (Box 7, Folder 50)
    - Letters of reference, A-B, 1982-92 (Box 7, Folder 51)
    - Letters of reference, H-W, 1982-92 (Box 7, Folder 52)
    - Students, 1973, 1977, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 53)
- SERIES V. WRITINGS
  - Published works
    - Books
      - Social Work Practice: People and Environments, 1979
        - Correspondence and pre-publication reviews, 1975-80, undated (Box 8, Folder 54)
        - Reviews (Box 8, Folder 54a)
      - The Life Model of Social Work Practice, 1980 (co-authored with Alex Gitterman)
        - Correspondence, 1975-87 (Box 8, Folder 55)
        - Pre-publication reviews, undated (Box 8, Folder 56)
        - Incomplete manuscript and contract for German edition, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 57)
        - Reviews (Box 8, Folder 57a)
      - Social Work Practice in Health Care, 1984
        - Correspondence, 1983-84 (Box 8, Folder 58)
        - Reviews (Box 8, Folder 58a)
      - Advances in Clinical Social Work Practice, 1985
        - Reviews (Box 8, Folder 58b)
      - Human Behavior in the Social Environment: An Ecological View, 1991
        - Correspondence, 1981-95 (Box 8, Folder 59)
        - Permissions, 1988-89 (Box 8, Folder 60)
        - Outline, pre-publication reviews, promotional brochure, undated (Box 8, Folder 61)
        - Research materials, Chapter 1, undated (Box 8, Folder 62-63)
        - Research materials, Chapters 2 and 3, undated (Box 8, Folder 64)
        - Research materials, Chapters 4 and 5, undated (Box 8, Folder 65-66)
        - Research materials, family chapters, general, undated (Box 9, Folder 67)
        - Research materials, family chapters, general, undated (Box 9, Folder 68)
        - Research materials, Instructor's Guide, undated (Box 9, Folder 69-70)
        - Computer disks and related correspondence, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 71)
        - Reviews (Box 9, Folder 71a)
      - Anthology of Ecological Social Work, 1992
        - Contract, 31 Aug 1991 (Box 9, Folder 72)
        - Correspondence with Alex Gitterman Dec 1987-Nov 1992 (Box 9, Folder 73)
        - Correspondence with Alex Gitterman Jan-Dec, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 74)
        - Correspondence with Alex Gitterman Jan-Dec 1994 (Box 9, Folder 75)
        - Correspondence with Alex Gitterman Jan-Jun, 1995, undated (Box 9, Folder 76)
        - Correspondence with publisher 1984-95 (Box 10, Folder 77)
        - Prospectus, undated (Box 10, Folder 78)
        - Research materials, undated (Box 10, Folder 79-81)
        - Typed manuscript, 1995
          - Section 1 (Box 11, Folder 82)
          - Section 2 (Box 11, Folder 83)
          - Section 3 (Box 11, Folder 84)
          - Section 4 (Box 11, Folder 85)
          - Section 5 (Box 11, Folder 86)
          - Instructor's Manual, Version 1 (Box 12, Folder 87)
          - Instructor's Manual, Version 2 (Box 12, Folder 88)
          - 5.25" computer disks, 1994, undated (Box 12, Folder 88a)
    - Research materials--unidentified
      - Probably for either Human Behavior in the Social Environment: An Ecological View, 1991 or The Life Model of Social Work Practice: Advances in Theory and Practice,1996 (Box 13-14, Folder 89-98)
    - Articles
      - "Social Study, Past and Future", 1968 (Box 15, Folder 99)
      - "An Ecological Perspective in Casework Practice", 1973 (Box 15)
      - "A Theoretical View of the Life Model: Eco-Systems Perspective", 1975 (Box 15)
      - "Social Work Practice: A Life Model", 1976 (Box 15)
      - "Time: An Ecological Variable in Social Work Practice", 1976 (Box 15)
      - "General Systems Theory and Ego Psychology: An Ecological Perspective",1978 (Box 15)
      - "Space: An Ecological Variable in Social Work Practice", 1978 (Box 15)
      - "People and Ideas in the History of Social Work Practice" (co-authored with Ann Hartman), 1980 (Box 15)
      - "Social Work Identity, Competence, and Autonomy: The Ecological Perspective", 1980 (Box 15)
      - "The Ecological Approach to People--Environment Transactions", 1981 (Box 15)
      - "Teaching Primary Prevention in Social Work: An Ecological Perspective", 1982 (Box 15)
      - Untitled: debate in Practice Digest, 1982 (Box 15, Folder 100)
      - "Time, Change, and Social Work",1983 (Box 15)
      - "Human Development in Contemporary Environments", 1987 (Box 15)
      - "Effectiveness of Natural Rural Helpers", 1988 (Box 15)
      - "Emerging Conceptions of Family Development Over the Life Course", 1990 (Box 15)
      - "An Instructor's Story About Students' Life Stories", 1991 (Box 15)
      - "Patterns of Natural Helping in Rural Areas: Implications for Social Work Research" (co- authored with S. Patterson, J. Memmott and E. Brennan), 1992 (Box 15)
      - "Emerging Conceptions of Family Development Over the Life Course", 1994 (Box 15)
      - Untitled: invited article in Issues in Social Work Education, undated (Box 15)
    - Research materials for "People and Ideas in the History of Social Work Practice" (co-authored with Ann Hartman), Social Casework 61 (6): 323-331, 1980 (Box 15, Folder 101)
    - Commentaries and reviews
      - 1974-90 (Box 15, Folder 102)
      - 1991-95, undated (Box 15, Folder 103)
    - Forewords, introductions and chapters
      - 1980-95 (Box 16, Folder 104)
      - Subject entries in Encyclopedia of Social Work, 1981, 1985, 1993, 1995 (Box 16, Folder 105)
      - Written debate in Controversial Issues in Human Behavior, Martin Bloom, ed., 1995 (Box 16, Folder 106)
  - Speeches
    - Conferences and symposia
      - 1970-74 (Box 16, Folder 107)
      - 1975-79 (Box 16, Folder 108)
      - 1980-81 (Box 16, Folder 109)
      - 1982-83 (Box 16, Folder 110)
      - 1984-86 (Box 16, Folder 111)
      - 1987-89 (Box 16, Folder 112)
      - 1990, undated (Box 16, Folder 113)
    - Commencement, convocation and miscellaneous addresses, 1971-87 (Box 16, Folder 114)
  - Unpublished works
    - Dissertation: "Casework and Science: A Study in the Sociology of Knowledge"
      [See also Series II. Education]
      - Correspondence, institutional, 1968-68 (Box 18, Folder 115)
      - Correspondence, advisory, 1967-71 (Box 18, Folder 116)
      - Correspondence, publication, general, 1971-74 (Box 18, Folder 117)
      - Correspondence, publication, University of Chicago Press, 1971-72 (Box 18, Folder 118)
    - Research materials, undated (Box 18, Folder 119-121)
      - Typed manuscript, 1971
        - Chapters 1-4 (Box 19, Folder 122)
        - Chapters 5-6 (Box 19, Folder 123)
        - Chapter 7-epilogue (Box 19, Folder 124)
    - "Science and Humanism in Social Casework: The History and Sociology of an Idea System"
      - Typed manuscript, undated
        - Chapters 1-3 (Box 19, Folder 125)
        - Chapters 4-5 (Box 19, Folder 126)
        - Chapter 6-epilogue (Box 19, Folder 127)
    - "A History of Practice Theory in Social Work" (with Ann Hartman)
      - Research materials, undated (Box 20, Folder 128-129)
      - Typed manuscript (incomplete), bibliographies and references, undated (Box 20, Folder 130)
      - Correspondence, 1975-76, undated (Box 20, Folder 131)
    - Unidentified writings, 1995, undated (Box 20, Folder 132)
    - Typed essays, probably unpublished, 1983, 1985, undated (Box 20, Folder 133)
- SERIES VI. SUBJECTS
  - Addiction (Box 21, Folder 134-135)
  - Adolescence (Box 21, Folder 136-139)
  - Adulthood (Box 22, Folder 140-143)
  - AIDS (Box 22, Folder 144-145)
  - Census data (Box 23, Folder 146)
  - Children (Box 23, Folder 147)
  - Community (Box 23, Folder 148-153)
  - Death and dying (Box 24, Folder 154-155)
  - Divorce (Box 24, Folder 156)
  - Dubos, Rene (Box 24, Folder 157)
  - Elders and aging (Box 24, Folder 158-159)
  - Elders and aging (Box 25, Folder 160-166)
  - Empathy, friendship, non-traditional relationships (Box 26, Folder 167)
  - Empowerment (Box 26, Folder 168)
  - Environment, natural world (Box 26, Folder 169)
  - Ethics in social work (Box 26, Folder 170)
  - Family violence (Box 26, Folder 171-172)
  - Feminism, general (Box 26, Folder 173)
  - Feminism
    - "The 'Risk' of Essence" (Box 26, Folder 173a)
    - "Feminism and Methodology" (Box 26, Folder 173b)
  - Genetics (Box 26, Folder 174)
  - Health, healthcare (Box 27, Folder 175)
  - History and philosophy of science (Box 27, Folder 176)
  - History of social work (Box 27, Folder 177-179)
  - History of social work
    - "One Hundred Years of Social Work in Kansas: Beginning Before 1866 and Ending After 1966," by Esther E. Twente (Box 27, Folder 179a)
  - History of social work (Box 27, Folder 180-181)
  - History of social work (Box 28, Folder 182-187)
  - Homelessness (Box 28, Folder 188)
  - Homosexuality (Box 29, Folder 189-190)
  - Immigrants, minorities, refugees (Box 29, Folder 191-193)
  - Language (Box 29, Folder 194-195)
  - Legal (Box 29, Folder 196)
  - Life course theory (Box 30, Folder 197)
  - Marriage and couplehood (Box 30, Folder 198)
  - Mental illness (Box 30, Folder 199-202)
  - National Conference of Social Work: proceedings (incomplete), 1926-27, 1932, 1936-37, 1939, 1940-41 (Box 31, Folder 203-211)
  - National Conference of Social Work: proceedings (incomplete), 1942, 1948, 1954-56 (Box 32, Folder 212-215)
  - National Conference on Social Welfare (incomplete), 1957-58,1960-61 (Box 32, Folder 216-219)
  - Physical disability and chronic illness (Box 33, Folder 220-221)
  - Physical and emotional environment (Box 33, Folder 222-223)
  - Physical illness (Box 33, Folder 224)